<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>excerpt from Life of Samuel Richardson with Remarks on his Writings</title>
            <author>Anna Barbauld</author>
            <editor>Mary A. Waters edited this essay for The Criticism Archive.</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>CoDHR @ TAMU, Digital Editions, Start to Finish</publisher>
            <date when="2022-10-27">Fall 2022</date>
            <idno type="local">barbauld1804CX</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="main" level="a">LIFE OF SAMUEL RICHARDSON, WITH REMARKS ON HIS
                  WRITINGS.</title>
               <title type="sub">From The Correspondence of Samuel Richardson, author of
                     <title>Pamela</title>, <title>Clarissa</title>, and <title>Sir Charles
                     Grandison</title>. Selected from the original manuscripts, bequeathed by him to
                  his family, to which are prefixed, a biographical account of that author, and
                  observations on his writings, by</title>
               <author><name>Anna Letitia Barbauld,</name></author>
               <biblScope>6 Vols.</biblScope>
               <pubPlace>(London:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>printed for Richard Phillips, no. 71, St. Paul's Church-Yard, Lewis and
                  Roden, Printers, Paternoster-Row,</publisher>
               <date>1804),</date>
               <biblScope>1:vii-ccxii.</biblScope></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <head>
               <bibl>
                  <author><name ref="#BarbauldMrs">Anna Letitia Barbauld</name></author>
                  <hi rend="small">excerpt from the</hi>
                  <title type="main" level="m">
                     <hi rend="large">LIFE </hi>
                     <lb/>
                     <hi rend="smcaps">OF</hi>
                     <lb/>
                     <hi rend="large">SAMUEL RICHARDSON,</hi>
                     <lb/>WITH <lb/>
                     <hi rend="small">REMARKS ON HIS WRITINGS.</hi>
                     <note>From <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of <name
                              ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Samuel Richardson</name>, author of
                              <title>Pamela</title>, <title>Clarissa</title>, and <title>Sir Charles
                              Grandison</title>. Selected from the original manuscripts, bequeathed
                           by him to his family, to which are prefixed, a biographical account of
                           that author, and observations on his writings, by <name
                              ref="#BarbauldMrs">Anna Letitia Barbauld</name></hi>, 6 Vols. (London:
                        printed for Richard Phillips, no. 71, St. Paul's Church-Yard, Lewis and
                        Roden, Printers, Paternoster-Row, 1804), 1:vii-ccxii. Mary A. Waters edited
                        this essay for <ref
                           target="https://poetess.dh.tamu.edu/criticism/work/BarbLifeRichardson1804"
                           >The Criticism Archive</ref>.</note>
                  </title>
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <pb n="clxi"/>
            <p>[. . . .]</p>
            <p> The author of <title>Clarissa</title> was always fond of female society. He lived in
               a kind of flower-garden of ladies: they were his inspirers, his critics, his
               applauders. Connections of business apart, they were his chief correspondents. He had
               generally a number of young ladies at his house, whom he used to engage in
               conversation on some subject of sentiment, and provoke, by artful opposition, to
               display the treasures of intellect they possessed. <name ref="#ChaponeMrs">Miss
                  Mulso</name>, afterwards <name ref="#ChaponeMrs">Mrs. Chapone</name>; <name
                  ref="#DuncombeSusanna">Miss Highmore</name>, now <name ref="#DuncombeSusanna">Mrs.
                  Duncombe</name>; <name ref="#TalbotCatherine">Miss Talbot</name>, niece to <name
                  ref="#SeckerThomas">Secker</name>, and author of some much esteemed devotional
               pieces; <name ref="#PrescottMary">Miss Prescott</name>, afterwards <name
                  ref="#PrescottMary">Mrs. Mulso</name>; <name ref="#FieldingSarah">Miss
                  Fielding</name>s; and <name ref="#CollierJane">Miss Collier</name>s, resided
               occasionally with him. He was accustomed to give the young ladies he esteemed the
               endearing appellation of <pb n="clxii"/> his daughters. He used to write in a little
               summer-house, or grotto<note>The same of which an engraving is given in the work
                     [<name ref="#BarbauldMrs">Barbauld</name>'s note].</note>, as it was called,
               within his garden, before the family were up; and, when they met at breakfast, he
               communicated the progress of his story, which, by that means, had every day a fresh
               and lively interest. Then began the criticisms, the pleadings, for <name
                  ref="#HarrietByron">Harriet Byron</name> or <name ref="#Clementina"
                  >Clementina</name>; every turn and every incident was eagerly canvassed, and the
               author enjoyed the benefit of knowing before-hand how his situations would strike.
               Their own little partialities and entanglements, too, were developed, and became the
               subject of grave advice, or lively raillery. <name ref="#DuncombeSusanna">Mrs.
                  Duncombe</name> thus mentions the agreeable scene, in a letter to <name
                  ref="#PrescottMary">Mrs. Mulso</name>.</p>
            <quote>
               <p>I shall often, in idea, enjoy again the hours that we have so agreeably spent in
                  the delightful retirement of North End: </p>
            </quote>
            <quote>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l rend="indent6">For while this pleasing subject I pursue,</l>
                  <l rend="indent6">The grot, the garden, rush upon my view;</l>

                  <pb n="clxiii"/>
                  <!--silently corrected from cxliii-->
                  <l rend="indent6">There, in blest union, round the friendly gate, </l>
                  <l rend="indent6">Instruction, Peace, and chearful Freedom wait; </l>
                  <l rend="indent6">And there, a choir of list'ning nymphs appears </l>
                  <l rend="indent6">Oppress'd with wonder, or dissolved in tears; </l>
                  <l rend="indent6">But on her tender fears when Harriet dwells, </l>
                  <l rend="indent6">And love's soft symptoms innocently tells,</l>
                  <l rend="indent6">They all, with conscious smiles, those symptoms view, </l>
                  <l rend="indent6">And by those conscious smiles confess them true. </l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Mr. Richardson</name> was a friend to mental
               improvement in women, though under all those restrictions which modesty and decorum
               have imposed upon the sex. Indeed, his sentiments seem to have been more favourable
               to female literature, before than after his intercourse with the fashionable world;
               for <name ref="#ClarissaHarlowe">Clarissa</name> has been taught Latin, but <name
                  ref="#HarrietByron">Miss Byron</name> is made to say, that she does not even know
               which are meant by the learned languages, and to declare, that a woman who knows them
               is an owl among the birds. The prejudice against any appearance of extraordinary
               cultivation in women, was, at that period, very strong. It will scarcely be believed,
                  <pb n="clxiv"/> by this generation, that <name ref="#DelanyMrs">Mrs.
               Delany</name>, the accomplished <name ref="#DelanyMrs">Mrs. Delany</name>, objects to
               the words <hi rend="italic">intellect</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ethics</hi>, in one
               of the conversation pieces, in <title>Grandison</title>, as too scholastic to proceed
               from the mouth of a female. What would some of these critics have said, could they
               have heard young ladies talking of gases, and nitrous oxyd, and stimuli, and
               excitability, and all the terms of modern science. The restraint of former times was
               painful and humiliating; what can be more humiliating than the necessity of affecting
               ignorance? and yet, perhaps, it is not undesirable that female genius should have
               something to overcome; so much, as to render it probable, before a woman steps out of
               the common walks of life, that her acquirements are solid, and her love for
               literature decided and irresistible. These obstacles did not prevent the
                  <title>Epictetus</title> of <name ref="#CarterElizabeth">Mrs. Carter</name>, nor
               the volumes of <name ref="#ChaponeMrs">Mrs. Chapone</name>, from being written and
               given to the world.<pb n="clxv"/>
            </p>
            <p> The moral qualities of <name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</name> were crowned
               with a serious and warm regard for religion; it is conspicuous in all his works; and
               we shall, probably, not find any writings, of the class of novels, in which virtue
               and piety are so strongly and uniformly recommended, without any party spirit, or
               view to recommend a particular system, and it would be doing injustice to the taste
               of the world not to say that they were highly valued on that account. The house of
                  <name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</name> was a school of virtuous sentiment
               and good morals. The following letter, from <name ref="#ReichErasmus">Mr.
                  Reich</name>, of Leipsic, shews the pleasing impression a visit to him made on the
               lively feelings of a foreigner. </p>
            <quote>
               <p> You know, Sir, I set out for England purely with a view of cultivating a personal
                  acquaintance with so great a man as <name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Mr. Samuel
                     Richardson</name>, who had so long endeared himself to me by his works, and
                  who, afterwards, by the corres- <pb n="clxvi"/> pondence established between us,
                  granted me his friendship. I arrived at London the eighth of August, and had not
                  much difficulty in finding <name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Mr. Richardson</name> in
                  this great city. He gave me a reception worthy of the author of
                     <title>Pamela</title>, <title>Clarissa</title>, and <title>Grandison</title>;
                  that is, with the same heart which appears throughout his works. His person, his
                  family, and even his domestics, all answer this character. He carried me into his
                  library, and his printing-house, (for he is a printer), in both which I never saw
                  things so well disposed. Sunday following, I was with him at his country-house,
                  (Selby-house) where his family was, with some ladies, acquaintances of his four
                  daughters, who, with his lady, compose his family. It was there I saw beauties
                  without affectation; wit without vanity; and thought myself transported to an
                  inchanted land. After chocolate, <name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Mr.
                     Richardson</name> brought <pb n="clxvii"/> us into the garden, adjoining to the
                  house. He invited me to partake of its fruits, of which the trees afforded the
                  finest of their kind; and, perceiving that I hesitated, gathered some himself,
                  which he presented to me. Every thing I saw, every thing I tasted, recalled to me
                  the idea of the golden age. Here are to be seen no counterfeits, such as are the
                  offspring of vanity, and the delight of fools. A noble simplicity reigns
                  throughout, and elevates the soul. The harmony of this charming family furnished
                  me with many reflections on the common ill-judged methods of education, whence
                  springs the source either of our happiness or misery. The ladies affected not that
                  stiff preciseness peculiar to coquettes. Trained up by a parent who instructs
                  them, still more by his example than by his works, they strive to imitate him;
                  and, if you feel a tenderness for objects so lovely, you will <pb n="clxviii"/>
                  surely be sensible of a still greater respect for them. </p>
               <p> In the middle of the garden, over against the house, we came to a kind of grotto,
                  where we rested ourselves. It was on this seat, <name ref="#LeFevreJohn">Mr. Le
                     Fevre</name>, (<name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Mr. Richardson</name>'s friend)
                  told me, that <name ref="#PamelaAndrews">Pamela</name>, <name
                     ref="#ClarissaHarlowe">Clarissa</name>, and <name ref="#SirCharlesGrandison"
                     >Grandison</name>, received their birth; I kissed the ink-horn on the side of
                  it. We afterwards proceeded to table, (dinner,) where an opportunity was offered
                  me of reading the letters written to me by <name ref="#SackAntoinette">Malle.
                     Sack</name>, from Berlin, concerning my voyage, and Mr. <name
                     ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</name>. One might in them discern that wit
                  which is the peculiar characteristic of that lady; and, every one listened with
                  the closest attention to whatever truth obliged me to say concerning her.
                  Whereupon <name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Mr. Richardson</name> observed to me, that
                  the ladies in company were all his adopted daughters: that he should be very proud
                     <pb n="clxix"/> to give to them, as well as to his own, so charming a sister;
                  and desired to signify as much to her, and to send her his picture, which he gave
                  me for that purpose. The rest of our discourse turned on the merits of <name
                     ref="#GellertChristian">Mr. Gellert</name>, and of some other Germans of
                  distinction. I told him, we had the same reason to glory in our relationship, as
                  countrymen of these worthy gentlemen, as the English had in regard to him. <name
                     ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Mr. Richardson</name>'s usual modesty dictated his
                  answer. Towards evening he brought me to London, where he made me promise to come
                  and see him as often as I could. On the Sunday following I was with him again at
                  his pleasant country seat. We found there a large company, all people of merit;
                     <name ref="#MillerPhilip">Mr. Miller</name>, author of the <title>Gardener's
                     Dictionary</title>, (which has been translated at Nurnburg, with such success),
                  and <name ref="#HighmoreJoseph">Mr. Highmore</name>, the famous painter, <fw
                     type="vol">
                     <hi rend="smcaps">vol. i.</hi>
                  </fw>
                  <fw type="sig">h</fw>
                  <pb n="clxx"/> were there. This last, two days afterwards, conferred on me a
                  genteel piece of civility, which I shall never forget: he must, indeed, be the
                  accomplished gentleman he appears to be, by obliging with so good a grace. I was
                  extremely concerned on not seeing his only daughter, who was in the country. I
                  have read some of her letters, which excite in me the highest esteem both for her
                  understanding and her heart. In the evening I took my leave of the family, and
                  returned with <name ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Mr. Richardson</name>. I saw him
                  several times since, during the eight days I staid in England; but it was
                  necessary, at last, to quit that divine man. I gave him the letter entitled No. I.
                  he embraced me, and a mutual tenderness deprived us of speech. He accompanied me
                  with his eyes as far as he could: I shed tears. </p>
            </quote>
            <p> There is one fault of which it will not <pb n="clxxi"/> be easy to clear our author.
               It is said that he was vain; he was fed with praise, and, with regard to that diet,
               it may be truly affirmed, that </p>
            <quote>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>———— increase of appetite doth grow </l>
                  <l>By what it feeds on.<note>
                        <name ref="#ShakespeareWilliam">Shakespeare</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                           <title>Hamlet</title>
                        </hi> I.ii.143-4.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p> In the circle of his admirers, his own works occupied, naturally, a large share of
               conversation; and he had not the will, nor perhaps the variety of knowledge necessary
               to turn it on other topics. The same subject forms the prominent feature in his
               correspondencies.—Impartiality, perhaps, requires a biographer to notice the opinion
               of such a man as <name ref="#JohnsonSamuel">Johnson</name>, delivered through the
               medium of <name ref="#BoswellJames">Mr. Boswell</name>'s memory, as follows, giving
               an account of a conversation at <name ref="#NairneWilliam">Mr. Nairne</name>'s, where
                  <name ref="#JohnsonSamuel">Dr. Johnson</name> drew the character of <name
                  ref="#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</name>. "I only remember that he expressed a
               high value for his talents and virtues: But that his perpetual study <fw type="sig">h
                  2</fw>
               <pb n="clxxii"/> was to ward off petty inconveniences, and to procure petty
               pleasures; that his love of continual superiority was such, that he took care always
               to be surrounded by women, who listened to him implicitly, and did not venture to
               contradict his opinions; and that his desire of distinction was so great, that he
               used to give large vails to Speaker <name ref="#OnslowArthur">Onslow</name>'s
               servants, that they might treat him with respect."<note>
                  <name ref="#BoswellJames">James Boswell</name> paraphrasing <name
                     ref="#JohnsonSamuel">Dr. Johnson</name>. See <name ref="#BoswellJames"
                     >Boswell</name>'s <hi rend="italic">
                     <title>Life of <name ref="#JohnsonSamuel">Dr. Johnson</name>
                     </title>
                  </hi>, ed. George Birbeck, rev. L.F. Powell. 6 vols. (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1950)
                  5.395-6.</note>
            </p>
            <p> It may be observed upon this, that the ladies he associated with were well able to
               appreciate his works. They were both his critics and his models, and from their
               sprightly conversation, and the disquisitions on love and sentiment, which took
               place, he gathered what was more to his purpose than graver topics would have
               produced. He was not writing a dictionary, like <name ref="#JohnsonSamuel"
                  >Johnson</name>, or a history, like <name ref="#GibbonEdward">Gibbon</name>. He
               was a novel writer; his business was not only with the human heart, but with the
               female heart. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
